Okay, so the topic for today is threads and RPC,
好的，今天的主题是线程和 RPC ，
second lecture in 6.824,
6.824 第二讲，
again we're going to mostly look at threads and RPC in the context of Go,
我们将主要关注 Go 的线程和 RPC ，
you know programming language that we're using in the labs,
我们在实验中使用的编程语言，
and in fact most of this lecture is really tailored,
这节课的大部分内容都是量身定做的，
towords helping you do Go programming for the labs,
帮助你了解实验用的 Go 编程，
so all of you've done hopefully the tutorial and the crawler exercise,
希望你完成了入门教程和爬虫练习，
which we'll discuss them quite a bit of detail later in the lecture,
我们将在稍后的课程中详细讨论它们，
but before jumping into the details,
但在讨论细节之前，
let me a little bit more of code calling,
让我用更多的代码调用，
to break the [] and get people to ask questions.
来打破[]并让大家提问。
So maybe you can answer the question,
也许你可以回答这个问题，
where are you and how did you enjoy the tutorial,
你在哪里，你觉得这个教程怎么样，
what's your first impression to Go,
你对 Go 的第一印象是什么，
maybe I'll.
也许我会。
Yeah, how about Evan Feldman?
Evan Feldman 你觉得怎么样？
Hi, folks, I'm Batman,
大家好，我是 Batman ，
I'm in Newton, which is on the outskirts of greater Boston,
我在 Newton ，在大波士顿的郊区，
the tutorial was interesting,
这个教程很有趣，
it was my first exposure to you know an object oriented language,
这是我第一次接触到面向对象的语言，
so it's, it's kind of a change, a change in framework,
所以，这是一种框架的改变，
that was interesting to adapt to.
适应这一点很有趣。
Okay, how about Brendan Wall?
好的，Brendan Wall 怎么样？
Brendan, are you there?
Brendan ，你在吗？
Yes, I was just finding the unmute button,
是的，我只是在找取消静音按钮，
sorry, what was the question, I just joined.
抱歉，问题是什么，我刚加入。
Where are you and what is your first impressions of Go?
你在哪里，你对 Go 的第一印象是什么？
Yeah, it's, I had used to Go before, for an internship,
是的，我以前在实习中用过 Go ，
that was my first time actually dealing with the concurrency stuff,
那是我第一次处理并发的东西，
and I like Go, like really working with goroutine,
我喜欢 Go ，使用 goroutine 来工作，
so kind of, initially it was tricky to think through like,
一开始很难想清楚，
like as soon as the main thread and all the goroutines are ended,
比如主线程和所有的 goroutine 一起结束，
so kind of working through those early kind of conceptual issues,
解决早期的一些概念问题，
but it's interesting.
但这很有趣。
How about the [Connor Prisby]?
[Connor Prisby] 怎么样？
[Connor], are you there?
[Connor]，你在吗？
Okay, try somebody else, Dory Shen.
好的，试试其他人， Dory Shen 。
Hi, I'm in Cambridge right now,
嗨，我现在在剑桥，
and I found Go to be pretty interesting,
我发现 Go 非常有趣，
I thought like go through through the first part of the tutorial,
我把教程的第一部分看了一遍，
I like learning about the for loops and the way they do for loops,
比如我学习了 for 循环，以及它们 for 循环的方式，
I thought that was pretty interesting,
我觉得这很有趣，
and like the way it's kind of structured,
比如它的组成方式，
I think that I like the the threads,
我想比如线程，
and I found to be a little bit more difficult about,
我发现它有点难，
when it ended,
当它结束时，
like when sometimes the function would end before all the routines,
比如有时函数会在所有例程之前结束，
like ended,
[比如结束]，
so that was like interesting to think about,
所以这想起来很有趣，
and like I learned more about that,
我学到的更多，
so it's pretty cool, I liked it.
所以这很酷，我喜欢它。
Well, hope all of you gonna have a very positive experience with Go this semester.
好的，希望你们在这学期都会有一个好的 Go 的体验。
And so let me say a little bit like you know why Go?
让我说一下为什么使用 Go 吗？
In principle, you know there's a lot of programming languages,
理论上，有很多编程语言，
that you could have used for doing distributed programming,
可以用来做分布式编程，
and Go is absolutely not the only one,
Go 绝对不是唯一一个，
but some reasons why we why we chose Go in 6.824.
但我们在 6.824 中选择 Go 有一些原因。
You know first of all, it has good support for threads and RPC,
首先，它对线程和 RPC 有很好的支持，
and those two are very important for distributed programming,
这两点对于分布式编程非常重要，
so it makes sense to you know
所以这是有道理的，
Go there's a good match for that.
Go 与这个很匹配。
Second reason we like it a lot is
我们非常喜欢它的第二个原因是，
you know it has a garbage collector,
它有一个垃圾收集器，
and if you do shared memory style parallelism,
如果你做共享内存式的并发，
where multiple threads share a structure or variable,
多个线程共享一个结构体或变量，
then having a garbage collector is nice,
那么有垃圾收集器是很好的，
because then the threads don't have to decide,
因为这样线程就不用考虑，
who's the last thread that actually has a reference to this memory,
谁是最后一个引用了这个内存的线程，
and should therefore deallocated,
因此应该重新分配，
the garbage collector use takes care of all those problems,
垃圾收集器负责处理所有这些问题，
that's convenient.
这很方便。
It's type safe.
它是类型安全的。
It is simple, it's a reasonable simple programming language,
它很简单，是一种简单的编程语言，
quite easy to learn.
学起来很容易。
And in fact you know ideas,
这些想法，
hopefully you've got that experience with in Go tutorial,
希望你在 Go 教程中感受到了，
that I want you to Go tutorial,
你完成了 Go 教程，
you mostly got most of Go.
你就知道了 Go 的大部分。
And then finally, it actually have a compiler,
最后，它有一个编译器，
so it's compiled,
所以它是编译的，
unlike Python,
与 Python 不同，
or you know actually the compiler produces actually usable code,
或者编译器产生可用的代码，
so the runtime overhead is not as large.
所以运行时开销不是很大。
I guess sort of the final reason why 6.824 in Go,
我想 6.824 使用 Go 的最后一个原因，
is actually I enjoyed writing Go programs,
我很喜欢使用 Go 写程序，
and so that may be also an important reason.
这可能也是一个重要原因。
So what I'm gonna do is,
所以我要做的是，
I'm going to talk a little bit about threads in general, RPC in general,
我将简单介绍一下线程和 RPC ，
and you know talk a little bit about different aspects of programming with threads,
讨论一下使用线程编程的不同方面，
some of that is pretty tutorial,
其中一些是很好的教程，
you have seen this before you know my [apologies],
你在我[抱歉]之前见过的，
I'm gonna go reasonable quickly through it,
我会很快介绍它，
it's definitely not a comprehensive introduction to concurrent programming,
它不是对并发编程的全面介绍，
but hopefully enough to remind you of
但希望可以提醒你，
what the issues are and what you should look out for.
问题是什么，以及你应该注意的是什么。
And we also spend some time quite a bit of talk about the crawler.
我们还会花一些时间讨论一下爬虫。
And so I'll share you a solution,
所以我向你们分享一个解决方案，
that I have two solutions,
我有两个解决方案，
one using channels and ones using mutexes,
一个使用 channel ，另一个使用 mutex ，
and we'll go through both of them.
我们会把它们都看一下。
Any questions so far before I dive in.
在我开始之前，有什么问题吗？
Okay, what we get started with threads,
好的，我们从线程开始，
so thread is basically shorthand for a thread of execution,
线程是执行线程的简写，
in Go, thread called the goroutine,
在 Go 中，线程称为 goroutine ，
but everybody else, basically in the world Go, calls a thread of thread,
但是在 Go 的世界中，人们还称它为线程的线程，
and so the way to think about it is that,
所以，考虑这个问题的方法是，
when you do go run,
当你使用 go run 时，
you know the Go will create a process you know on your operating system,
Go 在你的操作系统上创建一个进程，
and in the side of process you know the Go runtime system,
在这个进程中，是 Go 运行时系统，
and when Go start,
当 Go 开始的时候，
it actually has one thread of execution, the main thread,
它只有一个执行线程，即主线程，
but then it has primitives to create new threads,
但是它有用于创建新线程的原语，
and so you can think about this,
所以你可以这样想，
those are many many threads of execution you know running in parallel.
这里有很多执行的线程并行运行。
You can think about a single thread is basically sort of a sequential program line,
你可以认为单线程是一种顺序程序行，
so the program has a program counter,
程序有一个程序计数器，
has his own stack,
有自己的栈，
and has his own set of registers,
并且有自己的一套寄存器，
and so this behaves like a sequential program,
所以这就像一个顺序程序，
you can execute instruction one and instruction two, and instruction three and four,
你可以执行指令一和指令二，以及指令三和指令四，
you know may make a procedure call allocate memory on the stack,
可能让过程调用在栈上分配内存，
and will return from a procedure call, recursive call,
从过程调用、递归调用返回，
all sort of you know standard sequence programming,
所有标准顺序编程，
just like happens about as a sequential thread basically.
就像一个顺序线程。
The interesting thing is that,
有趣的是，
you know the threads may actually share memory with other threads,
这些线程可能与其他线程共享内存，
since all the threads are running in the same address space,
因为所有线程都在相同的地址空间中运行，
the same operating system address space,
相同的操作系统地址空间，
which is the same process address space,
是相同的进程地址空间，
they can actually share memory,
它们可以共享内存，
so one thread can write location say you know 10,
所以，比如一个线程可以写位置 10 ，
and then other thread can actually read that location 10,
然后其他线程可以读取位置 10 ，
so that way they can actually communicate information.
这样它们可以交流信息。
One way to think about a thread too is,
另一种考虑线程的方式是，
to think about it as sort of an abstraction that are supported by the runtime,
将其视为运行库支持的某种抽象，
and the runtime as a number of operations on a thread,
运行时在线程上执行多个操作，
so one operation, you know we've seen many times,
一个操作，我们已经看过很多次了，
and you've seen you know many times to actually started, for create threads,
你已经看到过多次，来创建线程，
you know this is go syntax, the go keyboard.
这就是 go 语法， go 关键字。
Thread can exit,
线程可以退出，
generally this means the exit can implicit,
通常退出是隐式的，
like when a thread returns from this,
比如当一个线程从这里返回时，
if you create a function using go, go keyword,
如果你使用 go 关键字创建一个函数，
and you know return out of the function,
从函数中返回时，
then implicitly the thread exits.
那么这个线程就隐式退出了。
Go runtime also has a couple other of under the hoods operations,
Go 运行时还有几个高级操作，
if you will, one it can actually stop a thread,
如果你愿意，它可以停止一个线程，
for example, if a thread writes to a channel
比如，如果线程向 channel 写入数据，
and there's no reader on the channel yet,
而这个 channel 上没有读取者，
then the thread might get blocked,
那么这个线程可能会被阻塞，
and so the Go runtime stops the thread,
所以 Go 运行时停止这个线程，
puts it aside,
把它放在一边，
so it can actually run another thread on the processor,
这样可以在处理器上运行另一个线程，
and then maybe later on, resume that thread,
也许稍后会恢复那个线程。
so third primitive actually is resume the thread.
所以，第三个原语是 resume 线程。
And really what it means to stop resume thread is,
而 stop resume 线程的真正含义是，
basically taking the state of the thread,
获取线程的状态，
like the program counter stack pointer and the register,
比如程序计数器，栈指针和寄存器，
put it on the side, run another thread on the processor,
把它放在一边，在处理器上运行另一个线程，
and then at some point you know decided to resume the processor,
然后在某个时刻，决定恢复处理器，
which means basically loading the program counter stack pointer and the registers back into the processor,
也就是把程序计数器，栈指针和寄存器加载回处理器，
so they start to run it.
让它开始运行。
So that's sort of a very mechanical view of what thread is.
这是对线程的一种非常[机械的]看法。
So why you have threads,
那么为什么要有线程，
in the first place, that seems like an important point to discuss.
这是一个值得讨论的重要问题。
Because in some ways,
因为在某些情况下，
the only thing threads do is,
线程唯一能做的是，
make your life more complicated as a programmer,
让你作为程序员的生活变得更加复杂，
you know like writing sequential code is actually easier than writing parallel code.
比如编写顺序代码比编写并行代码更容易。
The main reason to have it,
有它的主要原因是，
the main reason we care a lot about in 6.824 is to express concurrency,
在 6.824 中，我们非常关心的主要原因是表示并发性，
and sort of three different types or two or three different types of concurrency,
有两三种不同类型的并发性，
that we actually care about,
是我们关心的，
so we think about our process,
所以，考虑我们的进程，
we have runtime with our thread running.
我们有运行时运行线程。
You know one type of concurrency that we care a lot about is IO concurrency,
我们非常关心的一种并发类型是 IO 并发，
so one of these threads that running here,
所以有一个线程在这里运行，
it might actually make a network call,
它可能在做一个网络调用，
connect to another machine on the network,
通过网络连接到另一台机器，
you know to implement a distributed application, like mapreduce,
为了实现分布式应用程序，比如 mapreduce ，
and you know as it makes a call,
当它发起一个调用，
you know it's gonna be blocked, waiting for a response,
它会被阻塞，等待回复，
and when it's blocked and waiting for a response,
当它被阻塞，等待回复时，
everything you need to actually run some other threads.
你需要的是运行一些其他线程。
So that we're sort of [] more,
所以我们[]更多，
we're done,
我们运行，
for example, we want to issue multiple requests
比如我们要发出多个请求，
and multiple machines roughly in parallel,
多台机器大致并行，
you know we could just do that with fire off one goroutine
我们可以发起一个 goroutine 去做，
and the fire in another goroutine, another goroutine,
发起另一个 goroutine ，另一个 goroutine ，
that all kind of sent and make connections to other remote machines.
所有发送，连接到其他远程机器上。
That's one reason we care a lot about it, IO concurrency.
这是我们非常关心它的原因之一， IO 并发性。
The second reason that we care about is,
我们关心的第二个原因是，
you know allows for multi-core parallelism.
允许多核并行。
So we have a multiple cores,
所以我们有多个核心，
you know are you know computer or processor,
计算机或处理器，
then we can have one thread running on,
然后我们让一个线程运行，
one goroutine running on one core,
一个 goroutine 运行在一个核心上，
and another thread or another goroutine running on another core,
另一个线程或另一个 goroutine 运行在另一个核心上，
just straight in parallel.
直接并行。
And for example we implement a key-value servers,
比如，我们实现了键值服务器，
then we could process request for different keys,
然后我们可以处理不同键的请求，
and key-value service use on different cores completely in parallel,
键值服务使用不同的核心并发，
increasing our throughput.
增加我们的吞吐量。
So those are the two main reasons that we care a lot about concurrency,
所以这是我们非常关心并发性的两个主要原因，
but threads, there's sort of a third reason,
但是线程，还有第三个原因，
and there's a little bit of convenience.
就是比较方便。
There's gonna be numerous cases in the lab,
实验里会有很多案例，
for example where we wanna have something happened periodically,
比如，我们希望定期执行一些事情，
maybe every second or every 200 milliseconds,
可能每隔一秒或每隔 200 毫秒，
and now we can just launch a thread or a goroutine for that,
现在我们可以为它启动一个线程或 goroutine ，
there's a sleep for 200 milliseconds,
有 200 毫秒的睡眠时间，
it does what it needs to do,
做它需要做的事情，
and then it goes back to sleep for 200 milliseconds,
然后它回到睡眠状态 200 毫秒，
so it's convenient to have these background activities,
所以执行这些后台活动是很方便的，
that need to be done periodically,
需要定期完成的，
and you can express that using threads,
你可以用线程来做，
of course you can express it in other ways,
当然你可以用其他方式，
the threads are actually convenient.
但线程是很方便的。
Another question that comes up often in,
另一个经常出现的问题是，
I think came up with some of the lecture questions,
在一些讲座中出现的问题，
so today like how many threads you create.
你可以创建多少线程。
And I think the Go designers, the way they want you to think about it is,
我认为 Go 设计者想要你考虑的是，
that you should create as many threads as you need,
你应该根据需要创建尽可能多的线程，
they're definitely not free,
它们肯定不是免费的，
they tie up some memory,
它们会占用一些内存，
because you're going to have a stack,
因为你会有栈，
there's performance overhead we're starting them,
这会带来性能开销，我们启动它们时，
but there's you should think about them as very lightweight,
但你应该认为它们非常轻，
also you should be encouraging or you're encouraged to create threads as you go.
你也被鼓励应该按需创建线程。
Any questions about sort of this basic reason why to have threads?
关于为什么要有线程的基本原因，有什么问题吗？
Okay, let me,
好的，让我，
then you know as I mentioned earlier,
就像我之前提到的，
threads actually have challenges,
线程面临着挑战，
programming with threads has challenges,
使用线程进行编程具有挑战，
so let me talk a little bit about the challenges.
所以，让我来谈谈这些挑战。
I'm not going to go great amount of depth here,
我不打算在这里深入探讨，
I I assume that you know there's a they all make sense,
我希望它们是能理解的，
and will become more clear if we look at some of the examples.
如果我们看一些例子，就会变得更清楚。
And probably the main reason that you know threads and you're challenging is that,
可能线程具有挑战性的主要原因是，
you can have race conditions.
你会有竞态条件。
And just like a basic example of race condition,
比如一个基本的竞态条件，
let's say you have two threads,
假设你有两个线程，
you know, here's t1, here's t2,
这是 t1 ，这是 t2 ，
and they share variable n,
它们共享变量 n ，
let's say the initial value 0,
假设初始值为 0 ，
and they both execute,
它们都执行，
you know both execute statement, the form you know adds n increment n by 1,
都执行 n = n + 1 的语句，
and of course you might think that statement is an atomic operation
当然，你可能会认为这个语句是原子操作，
or something that is indivisible,
或者是不可分割的，
but it isn't,
但事实并非如此，
I mean there's a Go statement has compiled to
Go 语句会编译成，
whatever instructions the processor is executing,
处理器正在执行的指令，
so we cannot assume that an atomic instruction
所以我们不能假设这是原子指令，
and in fact, you know it's,
实际上它是，
it could consist of basically like a load,
它可能包含一个 load ，
you know which stores the n, the content of n to register,
将 n 的内容存入寄存器，
then increment register,
然后递增寄存器，
and then you know store of register back into memory.
然后，将寄存器取回到内存。
So if you're very unlucky,
所以如果你非常不走运，
you know the two threads basically try to,
这两个线程都试图，
both execute this particular instruction,
执行这条特定的指令，
then we can have a very you know unfortunate sequence of events,
然后我们会有一个糟糕的事件序列，
where like both threads you know perform the load instruction,
其中，两个线程都执行 load 指令，
load variable in you know register let's say r0,
加载变量到寄存器 r0 中，
you know here also in r0,
这边也在 r0 中，
you know then increment, so r0 becomes 1, 1,
然后增量，所以 r0 变成 1 1 ，
and then write it back to you know store instruction,
然后使用 store 指令把它写回，
that results results back into the variable n in memory.
把结果写回到内存中的变量 n 中。
And, so, if this happens at this particular,
所以，如果在这种情况下，
in this scenario, where this happens are truly concurrently,
在这种场景下，是真正并行的，
you know what is the value of n after these two threads that both increment.
那么在这两个线程都递增之后， n 的值是多少。
Just 1.
是 1 。
Yes, 1,
是的， 1 ，
and what is what is this value supposed to be,
这个值应该是什么，
what do we expect it to be.
我们期望它是什么。
2.
2.
Yeah, expect it to be 2, right,
是的，希望它是 2 ，
so, 1 is definitely not equal to 2 and there's a bug.
所以， 1 肯定不等于 2 ，这里有一个错误。
And so, and this is like you know the sort of heart of race conditions,
所以，这就是竞态条件的核心，
which is you know if an unfortunate sequence of events,
如果线程是糟糕的事件队列，
where threads share you know state,
线程共享状态，
the updates actually might not be reflected correctly,
更新可能会没有正确反映出来，
and of course most of the time, this will workout fine,
当然，大多数情况下，这都会正常工作，
because you just have to be in this sort of very,
因为你必须处于这个非常，
sort of this very specific case,
处于这个非常特殊的条件，
before it shows up.
在它出现之前。
So general, I think one of you reported,
通常情况下，你们中有人报告说，
like oh I didn't have my locks on my race,
我没有对我的竞态条件加锁，
you know I've been watching order
我一直查着顺序，
and my program just worked fine,
我的程序运行得很好，
and that's actually the real issue with race conditions,
这就是竞态条件的真正问题所在，
they typically just work fine,
它们通常工作得很好，
but sometimes it goes wrong.
但有时会出错。
So there are two ways to [address] race conditions.
所以，有两种方法可以解决竞态条件。
The first way is to avoid sharing,
第一种方法是避免分享，
don't share variables.
不要共享变量。
And this is one style of programming that you know Go encourages,
这是一种 Go 鼓励的编程风格，
by using channels,
通过使用通道，
channels use communicate values,
通道用来通信值，
but you don't really directly share memory,
但你并不需要直接共享内存，
so that's one way of doing it.
所以这是一种方法。
So avoid sharing one big approach,
所以避免共享一种方法，
the other approach is actually to use locks,
另一种方法是使用锁，
you know to make a sequence of instructions in atomic operation,
让一系列指令变为原子操作，
we'll talk a lot more about that in a second.
稍后我们会更详细地讨论这个。
One of the things I want to point out,
我想指出的一点是，
that is really cool,
这真的很酷，
that a useful tool,
一个实用的工具，
is Go actually have a race detector,
Go 其实有一个竞态检测器，
and most of the labs that you will doing,
你将要做的大多数实验，
would encourage you basically run Go using the -race flag,
推荐你运行 Go 使用 -race 标志，
and that will actually not catch every possible race,
这虽然不能捕捉所有可能的竞争，
but it does an extremely good job of actually identifying races,
但它在识别竞争方面做得非常好，
and so you should by default run Go with the race detector enabled.
所以，默认情况下，你应该在启用竞争检测器的情况下运行 Go 。
Okay, so that's one challenge with threads.
好的，这是一个关于线程的挑战。
The second challenge with threads actually coordination.
第二个关于线程的挑战是协调。
So it's often the case that one has to,
它通常情况下是，
you know one thread must wait another thread,
一个线程必须等待另一个线程，
before something is accomplished,
在完成某件事之前，
you know number of the Go exercise in the tutorial have a [form],
教程中的很多 Go 练习有这种形式，
and there's two ways, you know Go actually two primitives,
有两种方式， Go 有两个原语，
dealing with one again channels,
处理它的一个是通道，
channels basically allow you to communicate and to coordinate at the same time,
通道允许你同时通信和协调，
or you know we talk a little bit later about you know condition variables,
或者，我们稍后会讨论条件变量，
and both can be useful,
两者都很有用，
I'll talk a little bit more about that.
我会更多地谈到这一点。
And then finally there's sort of final challenge,
最后的挑战是，
a big sort of conceptual challenges is you can get deadlock,
一个大的挑战是死锁，
so if one thread waits,
所以，如果一个线程等待，
like t1 waits for t2 and t2 waits for t1,
比如 t1 等待 t2 ，而 t2 等待 t1 ，
you know for example to release your lock before some other sequence,
比如在其他程序之前，释放你的锁，
you can basically so what they call deadly embrace,
它们称为死锁，
you know where both waiting on the other,
双方都在等待对方，
as a result nothing makes for progress.
结果是什么都没有取得进展。
A trivial way you're getting you know deadlock in Go would be,
一种微不足道的 Go 的死锁方式是，
like you have a single thread,
比如你只有一个线程，
there's no other threads at all,
根本就没有其他线程，
and you're write to channel,
而你在写入通道，
and that will block that one thread,
这会阻塞那个线程，
until somebody else you know read, some other read from the channel,
直到其他人从通道中读取，
but if there's no other thread at all,
但如果根本没有其他线程，
you know that will result in a deadlock,
这会导致死锁，
like the simplest possible deadlock possible,
就是最简单的可能的死锁，
you know Go actually will catch this case,
Go 会抓住这种情况，
and will run raise a runtime error,
抛出运行时错误，
saying like no threads going to run, you have a deadlock.
表示没有线程可以运行，你有一个死锁。
But there could be more complicated deadlock were involved multiple threads,
但是如果涉及多个线程，可能会出现更复杂的死锁，
as you're going through the labs and the semester,
当你通过实验和学期的学习时，
you I'm sure you were on into some.
我肯定你会遇到一些。
So take a little bit of step back here,
所以往后退一步，
and think about Go for you know these challenges,
考虑 Go 的这些挑战，
that I just talked about.
我刚才谈到的。
Roughly speaking, Go has sort of two plans,
粗略地说， Go 有两个方案，
to handle these concurrency challenges.
来应对这些并发挑战。
And one plan is you know basically around channels,
一个方案是通过通道，
and there's another plan basically around locks and condition variables.
另一个方案上是通过和条件变量。
And the way I think about it,
在我看来，
you know some people are quite dogmatic about this,
有些人对此相当武断，
if one plan is better than the other plan,
是否一个方案比另一个方案好，
my general approach here is,
我在的总体方案是，
like I really look a plan that is most suitable for the case that I'm looking at,
我找一个更适合我的方案，
what I'm running into.
我要运行的。
And generally you know I've no sharing,
一般来说，我不会共享，
and basically I need two threads basically to communicate,
我需要两个线程通信，
but I don't really share any memory,
但我不共享内存，
I tend to use you know channels.
我倾向于使用通道。
If there are two threads I can do share memory,
如果有两个线程可以共享内存，
because it's convenient to share memory,
因为共享内存很方便，
for example I write a key-value service,
比如，我编写一个键值服务，
and I want to share the key-value table,
我想要共享键值表，
then I use locks and condition variables.
然后我使用锁和条件变量。
And so you know my general approach is not to be dramatic,
所以，我的总体方法不是[戏剧性]的，
and you know take whatever approach
可以采取任何方法，
gonna actually is most convenient for the problem that has.
对解决问题是最方便的。
The tutorial does a pretty good job of actually teaching about channels
这个教程很好地讲了通道，
mentioned locks, doesn't seem much about condition variables,
提到了锁，不太涉及条件变量，
so I I think it's worthwhile to talk a little bit about condition variables
所以我认为有必要讨论一下条件变量，
to make sure that you are aware that they exist.
确保你知道它们的存在。
And I'm going to do that using a tiny little example,
我会使用一个很小的例子来说明，
to illustrate the issues,
为了说明这些问题，
attending a little example is,
这个小例子是，
we have a little bit inspired,
我们有一点启发，
it's a little bit inspired by the labs,
它是受实验启发的，
and have a thread t1
有一个线程 t1 ，
and t1 needs to collect a number of votes
t1 需要收集一些选票，
you know from remote machines,
从远程机器上，
for example needs to decide that it has a majority,
比如，需要确定它拥有多数席位，
so that actually proceeds to commit some value,
所以，可以提交一些值，
and you'll see that later in like this shows up in the raft lab,
稍后你会在 raft 实验里看到，
as one of the primitives that you need,
作为你需要的原语之一，
and so to do that,
要做到这一点，
you know the t1 will fork you know other threads say t2,
t1 会 fork 出其他线程，比如 t2 ，
and t2 amazingly it don't does something expensive,
t2 不会做一些昂贵的事，
like you know talk to some remote machine to actually get its vote,
只是通过与远程机器通信来获得选票，
and then report back you know that vote to t1,
然后向 t1 报告投票结果，
and t1 basically need to collect all the votes held them up,
t1 需要收集它们获得的所有选票，
and then [] that majority,
然后达到大多数，
then declare sort of victory.
然后宣布胜利。
So there's a pretty straightforward simple program,
所以有一个相当简单的程序，
I'm going to give you a little bit,
我要给你们展示一下，
it allows me to illustrate you a couple of issues,
它让我可以说明几个问题，
we're going to switch to another screen.
我们要切换到另一个屏幕。
Can everybody see this?
都能看到这个吗？
So, here I have a very simple implementation of this program,
所以，这里我有一个非常简单的程序，
the vote thing,
投票的事情，
and again it's a little bit of a toy example,
这又是一个像玩具的例子，
that hopefully gets the point across.
希望让人们理解这一点。
The two variables shared here count and finished,
这里两个变量共享 count 和 finished ，
count count number of votes,
count 统计投票数，
finished count when we're done,
finished 表示我们已经完成，
so you know there's a loop going for 10,
这里有一个 10 次的循环，
creating a Go creating [launching] and anonymous function,
创建一个 Go 的匿名函数，
and anonymous function concurrently calls this function requestVote,
匿名函数并行调用函数 requestVote ，
requestVote basically you know simulates
requestVote 模拟
doing a long expensive operation on some remote machine,
在远程机器上执行一项长时间昂贵的操作，
and the way it simulates, it was by just going to sleep,
它模拟方式是使用 Sleep ，
it block for a little while, then it returns,
它会阻塞一段时间，然后返回，
and then you know the returns vote is yes,
然后如果返回的投票是肯定的，
then the count goes up,
那么 count 增加，
and count in fact that actually we have one more thread voting,
实际上，如果我们再有一个线程投票，
and then we're done,
然后我们就完成了，
and so that's actually fork off 10 threads,
所以会 fork 出 10 个线程，
you know each do requestVote and report the results,
每个线程都会调用 requestVote 并报告结果，
and then at the end,
然后在最后，
we'll check if the count smaller than 5,
我们会检查 count 是否小于 5 ，
you know we know that we failed, lost the election,
这里我们知道我们失败了，输掉了选举，
and if we have votes equal larger than 5,
如果我们的票数大于等于 5 ，
we'll basically won the election,
我们就赢得了选举，
so this sort of simple, a very simple program.
所以这是一个非常简单的程序。
Does it all make sense?
这个能理解吗？
Let me run it, you know for the kicks.
让我来运行它，只是为了好玩。
Then, you know we're running a couple times,
我们要运行几次，
something lose, something win, you know makes sense.
有些输了，有些赢了，这是合理的。
And so this program looks working and correct,
所以这个程序看起来工作正常而且是正确的，
is it actually correct?
它真的是正确的吗？
Sorry, is that a question,
抱歉，这是个问题吗，
whether this program is actually correct.
这个程序是否是正确的。
Yeah it seem to produce results.
是的，它似乎产生了结果。
I think there's a race condition is in there,
我认为这里有一个竞态条件，
like you have all of these different threads implementing the count and finished variables.
比如所有不同线程都实现了 count 和 finished 变量，
And it's also, it's not clear to me,
而且，我也不清楚，
that finished necessarily always reaches 10,
那个 finished 必须达到 10 ，
is it possible that it doesn't.
有没有可能它不会。
Let me, let me take these one by one
让我把这些一一拿出来，
and then go for your first point,
然后看你的第一个观点，
which is really what I was after,
这才是我真正想要的，
you know clear this as, a fact,
很明显这是，
we have two variables here, correct, you know count finished,
我们这里有两个变量， count finished ，
they're access by different goroutines,
它们被不同的 goroutine 访问，
so this is immediately a red flag,
所以这是一个明显的危险信号，
that could be a serious problem here,
可能是一个严重的问题，
as soon as you have a variable,
一旦你有一个变量，
that has access to or modified and by two different goroutines,
可以由两个不同的 goroutine 访问或修改，
you know there's gonna be a problem,
这里会有一个问题，
and so interesting to run the Go race detector,
所以运行 Go 竞争检测器，
it actually catches it.
它会抓住它。
And as you expect,
如你所料，
you know the Go the race detector tells you
Go 竞争检测器告诉你，
exactly you know there's indeed some problems here in this program
这个程序里确实有一些问题，
and list the line number or things actually go wrong.
并列出出问题的行号。
So it gives you a pretty good clue,
所以它给你提供了一个很好的线索，
that something is not up to [] this program,
表示有些东西不符合[]这个程序，
and so we're going to repair it in more steps,
所以我们分几步来修复它，
and you know that will hopefully shed some more light on computer programming.
希望为计算机编程带来更多的启示。
So let me give you my second solution to this program.
所以让我给出这个程序的第二个解决方案。
In this case,
在这种情况下，
we'll talk about channels a little bit later,
我们将在稍后讨论通道，
because I wanted to illustrate locks and condition variables first,
因为我想先说明锁和条件变量，
because they've got less emphasis in the tutorial.
因为它们在教程中强调比较少。
So you know a simple solution,
所以一个简单的解决方案，
you know Go correct introduce a lock,
Go 引入一个锁，
the lock is completely independent of the variables
锁完全独立于变量，
and you follow some convention,
你遵循一些惯例，
which says like, well this lock mu protects count and finished,
这个锁 mu 保护 count 和 finished ，
and so whenever you know you access count finished,
所以，当你访问 count finished 时，
basically you have to wrap that into the lock and unlock statements,
你必须将其包装到 lock 和 unlock 语句中，
and so here we see two like this is there Go function runs concurrently,
我们在这里看到两个 go 函数同时运行，
and after you know the requestVote,
在 requestVote 之后，
it's about of the vote and finished,
是关于投票核 finished 的，
we take a lock out,
我们对它加锁，
and then Go has this nice feature called defer statement,
然后 Go 有一个很好的特性， defer 声明，
that if you exit the basic block,
如果你退出基本区块，
you know will run, will run the function that is declared by defer,
将会运行由 defer 声明的函数，
after the keyword defer,
在关键字 defer 之后，
so this means like we execute,
这意味着我们可以执行，
we leave the Go function here will automatically unlock,
我们让 Go 函数可以自动解锁，
this is convenient, because then you won't forget to unlock,
这很方便，因为那样你就不会忘记解锁了，
so it's nice to do that write point where you do the lock,
所以，它很适合写到加锁的地方，
and so you can write immediately defer unlock
所以你可以直接写 defer unlock ，
and then you don't have to worry about,
然后你就不必担心，
if there are multiple exit pass out of the goroutine or ever function,
如果有多个 exit 通过 goroutine 或函数，
that you forget to unlock.
你可能会忘记解锁。
So now you know we're basically in the critical section,
所以现在我们在临界区域，
where we hold the lock,
我们持有锁，
we update vote count,
我们更新投票 count ，
and then of course the function returns and unlocks automatically.
然后函数返回并自动解锁。
Similarly, at the, at the, at the end,
同样地，在最后，
you know we got, when every time we access you know count finished,
当我们每次访问 count finished 时，
since they share,
因为它们是共享的，
you know we need to round it with locks,
我们需要用锁把它围起来，
and a simple way of doing that,
有一个简单的方法，
we could have written defer unlock here too in the body,
我们也可以在这里写 defer unlock ，
that will being fine, right.
这样就可以了。
So we can actually run this program,
所以我们可以运行这个程序，
let's see.
让我们看看。
And so we run it,
所以我们运行它，
you know the race detector seems to be happy,
竞争检测器看起来没问题，
so hopefully we'll have a better program.
希望我们有一个更好的程序。
All right?
好的?
So I just have a question here about scoping,
我有一个关于作用域的问题，
so it seems that when we have the anonymous function,
看起来，当我们有匿名函数时，
then we have mu,
然后我们有 mu ，
and we have the count and we have the finished,
我们有 count 和 finished ，
and it seems that the anonymous function has access to
看起来匿名函数可以访问
the [variable] defined outside the function,
函数外部定义的变量，
so how the scoping rules work?
那么作用域是如何工作的？
Yeah, you've been any,
是的，任何，
with an anonymous function,
在一个匿名函数中，
any variable that's used inside of the function is not declared inside a function,
在函数中使用的不是在函数中声明的任何变量，
basically resolve points to variables outside of the outer scope,
会指向外部作用域的变量，
so static scope.
也就是静态作用域。
What about the scope of like the mutex,
像互斥锁的作用域呢，
like how many times you have to declare that,
比如你要声明多少次，
or what's the scope of it, I guess.
或者它的范围是什么。
The scope of the defer statement is this block, one basic block.
defer 语句的作用域是这个基本块。
No, I mean like,
不，我的意思是，
when you actually declare like the mutex data structure, I guess.
当你声明互斥锁数据结构时。
Like any other variable,
像任何其他变量一样，
it has the same scope as finished or count.
它的作用域与 finished 或 count 相同。
So it applies to any variable declared in the rest of the.
所以它与其余部分中声明的任何变量。
Yeah, the way to think about is that,
是的，我们可以这样想，
the mutex is not directly associated with any variable,
互斥锁不直接与任何变量相关联，
it's just a lock, it's like a name,
它只是一把锁，一个名字，
and it's up to you as a programmer to decide what the lock protects,
作为程序员，你可以决定锁保护的是什么，
but there are two independent concepts.
但是有两个独立的概念。
What happens, what happens if you use i in the goroutine,
如果你在 goroutine 中使用 i 会发生什么，
that won't work, right, you need to pass that in.
那是不行的吧，你需要把它传进去。
Yeah, so whatever that's a good question,
是的，这是个好问题，
and then the number be, the number of you asked from email too,
你们中很多人在邮件中问过，
so what yeah what happens to,
所以会发生什么，
like if we use i here,
如果我们在这里使用 i ，
and they want to do something with it,
用它做点什么，
like whatever count is i,
比如 count = i ，
is a good plan or not?
这是不是可行的？
What value of i will be using,
i 会是什么值，
when this thread actually happens to run,
当这个线程运行时，
if Go starts to function function and will run at some point,
如果 go func 在某个时刻运行，
what value i will use it.
i 会是什么值。
Whatever i happens to be at the time,
i 会是那个运行时刻的值，
which is being changed by the for loop outside.
被外部的 for 循环修改。
Yeah, so and so this is not so great,
是的，所以这并不是很好，
it does probably not what we intended,
它可能不是我们想要的，
we probably intended to i we whatever for that loop iteration, right,
我们希望 i 对应那次循环，
so how do we want to,
那么我们要如何做，
if we have to solve, how would we do.
如果我们必须解决，我们要怎么做。
You could add it as a parameter to the anonymous function and pass it in,
你可以把它作为匿名函数的参数，并把它传进去，
so it gets evaluated, we create goroutine.
所以它会在创建 goroutine 时被求值。
Yeah, so would write this,
是的，所以我写下这个，
and then pass it in, right,
然后传进去，
then at a point what happens,
在这个时刻会发生，
then at the point, we actually create goroutine,
在我们创建 goroutine 的这个时刻，
i is being captured, and then passed it.
i 被捕获，然后传参。
Okay?
好的?
I also, how are the local variables allocated,
我还有个问题，局部变量是怎么分配的，
like if if count finished are like local variables,
比如 count finished 是本地变量，
wouldn't they like be destroyed after the main function exits,
它们不会在主函数退出后被销毁吗，
like if this function made by another function,
比如这个函数是由其他函数创建的，
what is like the [hitting] function existed before goroutine.
如果[命中]函数在 goroutine 之前退出会怎样。
The principal allocated in stack,
主体分配在栈中，
and you know the presumably the other functions,
可能其他函数，
there's memory addresses references to them,
有指向它们的内存地址，
so it's indeed the case,
所以是这样的，
its main returns,
它的主函数返回了，
then these you know the stack allocated variables are gone,
那么这些栈分配的变量就消失了，
so typically what you'll see is in a Go program,
所以通常你会在 Go 程序中看到，
you would allocate, I mean you know on the heap,
你会在堆上分配，
using new if you make a new struct or whatever.
使用 new 创建一个新的结构体。
So you get a segmentation fault then, or would.
所以，你会遇到段错误，或者。
Yeah, we'll get.
是的，我们会得到。
Okay.
好的。
I have a question,
我有一个问题，
I not remember this is the correct way to do it or not,
我不记得这是不是正确的方法，
but instead of passing it in,
但是除了把它传递进去，
would it be possible to as the first line in the for loop,
是否可以在 for 循环的第一行，
do i colon equals i,
使用 i := i ，
and then you're like you have a,
然后你有一个，
I don't know how the scoping works within the like block of the for loop,
我不知道作用域在 for 循环中是如何工作的，
because I think that should create a new variable i,
因为我认为这会产生一个新的变量 i ，
that the goroutine can access,
goroutine 可以访问，
that isn't being updated again.
并且不会再次更新。
Yeah, you can do that.
是的，你可以这样做。
That can help instead passing in, kind of makes it look ugly to me.
这可以避免传入参数，不过有点难看。
Okay, I I like passing in,
好的，我喜欢传参，
but that's another way of doing it,
但这是另一种方式，
I'll shows an example later.
稍后我将展示一个示例。
So somebody asked actually you know,
所以有人问，
do we get a segmentation fault,
我们会不会遇到段错误，
we're not immediately going to get a segmentation fault,
我们不会直接得到段错误，
actually take that back,
往回一点，
because basically one thread will still hold a reference,
因为一个线程仍然持有引用，
so the garbage collector will not delete the object yet,
所以垃圾回收器不会删除该对象，
that only when the last thread actually,
只有最后一个线程，
only when no thread holds a reference,
只有当没有线程持有引用时，
you know will the garbage collector delete the object,
垃圾回收器才会会删除该对象，
and these are one of the cool things
这是最酷的地方之一，
about having a garbage collected language and shared memory programming,
关于使用垃圾回收语言和共享内存编程，
you don't have to worry about that scenario.
你不必担心这种情况。
Okay, So.
好的，那么。
Yeah.
是的。
That would, could this code like deadlock,
这个代码会不会出现死锁，
because like if we if the goroutines,
因为如果 goroutine ，
like took the first for loop exit,
第一个 for 循环退出，
and then the second one will like,
然后第二个会，比如，
yeah, no, nevermind.
好的，没有关系。
Okay, there are definitely some issues that are not ideal yet,
好的，这里肯定有一些问题不完美，
so let me actually talk about them,
所以让我来谈谈它们，
one of them is that this particular loop a little bit annoying,
其中之一是这个循环有点烦人，
like there's this for loop is,
这个 for 循环是，
there's nothing else than waiting utill count reaches 5 finished,
除了等待 count 达到 5 ，没有别的，
and the way it does,
它这样做的方式，
it is about your spinning right,
它是在旋转，
so it locks locks locks at the value quickly,
所以它很快地对这个值加锁，
unlocks it and spins around again,
对它解锁，然后再次旋转，
so basically is spinning on the processor, doing really nothing,
所以就是在处理器上旋转，实际上什么都不做，
it would be nice to express that in a little bit better way,
应该有更好的方式来表示它，
so that basically the Go can give up the core again,
所以 Go 可以放弃核心，
so then another thread can run.
让另一个线程就运行。
And so the way you can do that is using condition variables,
这样做的方法就是使用条件变量，
and so this is my next implementation,
这是我的下一个实现，
or actually I show you one other implementation,
或者我向你展示另一个实现，
one way to do that,
一种完成的方法，
there's a little bit, not you know not so nice,
不是很好，
for example and somebody suggested,
比如，有人建议，
this is to actually sleep for a while,
在这里睡眠一段时间，
so instead of like giving up the spinning like crazy,
与其疯狂地放弃旋转，
just sleep one period,
只是睡眠一段时间，
sleep for a period and then come back.
睡一段时间，然后回来。
Of course, this solution will work,
当然，这个解决方案是有效的，
but the downside of it is,
但它的缺点是，
how long should you sleep, right,
你应该睡多久，
you really would like to be the case,
你很想这样，
that I assume for example this guy reaches 5,
比如，假设这个变量到了 5 ，
then you know you wake,
然后你唤醒，
you could wake up this particular you know the main thread.
你可以唤醒这个主线程。
And so I was jumping ahead a little bit,
所以我往前跳了一点，
but so that's what condition variables are for,
但这就是条件变量的作用，
you know here's a solution with condition variables,
这是使用条件变量的解决方案，
so, we allocated a new condition,
所以，我们分配一个新的条件，
here's condition variable allocated,
这里是分配条件变量，
it's associated with this particular lock,
它与这个锁关联，
we'll see in a second, why is important.
我们稍后会看到，为什么这很重要。
And you know basically the main thread what it does now,
现在的主线所做的，
it grabs the lock,
它获取锁，
because it needs to grab the lock to look at count and finished,
因为它需要获取锁来检查 count 和 finished ，
otherwise there could be a race conditions,
否则可能会有竞态条件，
and then if the condition is still not true,
然后，如果条件仍然不成立，
it just calls Wait on this condition variable,
它只是在这个条件变量上调用 Wait ，
and what that does is actually done atomically goes to sleep
它所做的是原子地进入睡眠状态
as well as releasing the lock that is associated with the condition variable,
并且释放与条件变量关联的锁，
since you know mu is actually associated the condition variable,
因为 mu 与条件变量关联，
can wait basically unlocks the lock and goes to sleep
可以等待解锁并睡眠，
in an atomic operation,
在一个原子操作中，
and when it returns from cond.Wait(),
当它从 cond.Wait() 返回时，
it will actually hold the lock again,
它会再次获得锁，
so the caller is, those are absolutely sure,
所以这些是肯定的，
that if caller returns will actually held the lock again,
如果调用者返回，将会再次持有锁，
so it's safe again to look at count and finished
所以，这也是安全地，查看 count 和 finished ，
and then call Wait again.
然后再次调用 Wait 。
Okay?
好的?
So basically you know this thread will go to sleep,
所以这个线程会进入睡眠状态，
and then the goroutines that are collecting the votes,
然后 goroutine 收集选票，
you know same code as before,
与之前相同的代码，
mu lock and unlock or defer unlock,
mu lock 和 unlock 或 defer unlock ，
and then when you're done,
然后当你完成时，
you know updating count finished,
更新 count 和 finished ，
there two primitives on condition variable,
条件变量上有两个原语，
one is Signal and one is Broadcast,
一个是 Signal ，一个是 Broadcast ，
and Broadcast, basically Signal waits of one waiter,
Signal 等待一个等待者，
Broadcast waits of all waiters,
Broadcast 等待所有的等待者，
there's only one waiter here,
这里只有一个等待者，
so we could have used either one of them.
所以我们可以用它们中的任何一个。
And so basically when it reaches you know 5,
所以当它达到 5 ，
you know some point or 10,
或者某些时刻是 10 ，
then you know, so every time finished is incremented,
所以每次 finished 递增，
you know the main thread will be woken up,
主线程会被唤醒，
you can check the condition and then keep going.
你可以检查条件，然后继续。
Okay?
好的?
So this is convenient,
所以这很方便，
so you can think about condition variables as
所以，你可以把条件变量看成
a coordination primitive between two different threads,
两个不同线程之间的协调原语，
and their particular convenient,
它们非常方便，
when you're actually using locks you know for to protect your shared state.
当你使用锁来保护你的共享状态时。
So here's the same implementation of this program using channels,
这是使用通道实现这个程序，
and more or less worked the same way,
基本上是一样的方式，
except with of course no locks,
当然除了没有锁，
but the main thread creates channel,
但是主线程创建通道，
passes the goroutine anonymous function,
传递 goroutine 匿名函数，
that's being created as a separate thread,
作为一个单独的线程创建，
you know writes basically the requestVote to the channel,
将 rquestVote 写入通道，
and then the main thread basically blocks here right,
然后主线程会在这里阻塞，
when it starts reading from channel,
当它开始从通道读取时，
Once it actually get something,
一旦它得到一些东西，
when something is written to the channel, will unlock,
当一些东西写入通道时，就会解锁，
you know look at the value and its true, add up,
查看值，如果为真，就累加，
and otherwise always increment finished.
否则， finished 总是递增的。
And what's going on here correct,
这里发生的一切，
we don't need locks,
我们不需要锁，
because count finished not shared,
因为 count 和 finished 没有共享，
there's only one thread that actually updates count and finished,
只有一个线程更新 count 和 finished ，
and that's the main thread.
也就是主线程。
Okay?
好的?
The.
这个。
And this this you know the the main,
这个主线程，
sorry, the requestVote thread you know all basically just write to this channel,
抱歉， requestVote 线程总是写入通道，
[] write concurrently perhaps in a channel,
可能在通道中并发写入，
but the channels are one of the things that Go that actually thread-safe,
但是通道是 Go 中线程安全的东西之一，
so multiple threads can actually write to the channel.
所以，多个线程可以写入通道。
Any questions about this, about the solution?
关于这个解决方案，有什么问题吗？
What was the thing about like having a buffer for the channel?
有缓冲的通道是怎么回事？
Yeah, so, normally when you're writing to the channel,
是的，通常情况下，当你写入通道时，
and nobody's reading from the channel
没有人从通道读取，
or no thread is reading from the channel,
或者没有线程从通道读取，
then the sender will immediately be blocked,
那么发送者会立即阻塞，
you can specify a channel has buffers of 10 or 20,
你可以指定一个缓冲区为 10 或 20 的通道，
and that allows the channel to have multiple values,
这会允许通道有多个值，
in in 6.824 labs,
在 6.824 实验中，
I've never used buffered channels,
我从来没有用过缓冲通道，
and one of two three times I did it,
我用过两三次，
I regretted it,
我后悔了，
so generally I don't use it.
所以我一般不用它。
But this is important point,
但这一点很重要，
this, this program is actually still not very good,
这个程序其实还不是很好，
for example, when,
比如，当，
it doesn't matter in practice in this particular example,
在这个例子中没有关系，
but it does in some the labs, that could might do,
但在某些实验中，可能会出现，
as soon as it reaches count 5 what will happen.
一旦 count 达到 5 ，就会发生什么。
It stops listening for a new channel,
它停止监听新的频道，
so any other threads are going to be blocked.
所以任何其他线程都会被阻塞。
Yeah, so basically it means like if the first 5 threads voted yes,
是的，这意味着如果前 5 个线程投了赞成票，
then the next 5 threads will be blocked in this channel, right,
那么接下来的 5 个线程将在这个通道中阻塞，
they'll be hanging around.
它们会被困住。
And in this case, it won't be a problem,
在这种情况下，这不会是一个问题，
because most of you guys are most observed that,
因为你们大多数人都注意到了，
if the main thread exit,
如果主线程退出，
it actually cleans up all the other threads too,
它也会清除所有其他线程，
but for example if this was a long running service,
但是如果这是一个长期运行的服务，
this would be not good,
这不是很好，
basically we're leaking threads here,
在这里我们会泄露线程，
you know they're getting blocked on the side,
它们阻塞在一边，
doing nothing in that channel,
在通道中什么都不做，
so that's quite inconvenient,
所以这很不方便，
and this is something to watch out for.
这是一个需要注意的东西。
And this showed up in the crawler,
这出现在爬虫上，
I think for many people in the,
我想对许多人来说，
and flip side of this is,
另一方面，
if the main thread exit too early before any of the requestVotes are done,
如果主线程在任何 requestVote 完成之前退出，
then you also have a problem,
那么你也有一个问题，
and so there's management of threads that actually is often a tricky issue.
所以，对线程的管理通常是一个棘手的问题。
Is there a way to kill the thread without exiting from main?
有没有在不退出主线程的情况下杀死线程？
Well, you can send it to a variable a value on some channels,
好的，你可以发送给一个变量到通道上，
seemed like please exit,
表示请退出，
but you have to coordinate it yourself.
但你必须自己协调它。
I'm gonna go back to one of the things that actually is cool about condition variables,
我要回到关于条件变量的一个很酷的事情上，
is that, in principle you might think you have the same issue exists here,
你可能会认为这里也存在同样的问题，
where like this thread actually runs,
这个线程运行，
and in this thread,
在这个线程中，
and it might get blocked,
它可能会被阻塞，
like for example if it reach you know 5,
比如，如果它达到 5 ，
you know this main thread will you know perceive doing its thing,
这个主线程在做它的事情，
while the other guys are still maybe actually sitting in here,
而其他线程可能还在这里，
notice these in this case, they won't be blocked,
注意在这种情况下，它们不会被阻塞，
because will grab the lock,
因为会获得锁，
then you know does the thing does a broadcast,
然后调用 Broadcast ，
the Broadcast is actually not a blocking operation,
Broadcast 不是阻塞操作，
so unlike you know writing to a channel,
所以不同于向通道写入，
that is a blocking operation,
那是一个阻塞操作，
if nobody is listening,
如果没有线程在接收，
the cond.Broadcast is not a blocking operation.
cond.Broadcast 不是阻塞操作。
So this actually works out in this particular program,
所以在这个项目中起作用的，
you know by itself correctly.
通过它自己。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, good.
好的，很好。
Any further questions about you know these two examples just to do?
关于这两个例子，还有什么问题吗？
Okay, then let's talk about the crawler,
好的，那我们来谈谈爬虫，
so the crawler is also a more realistic example of concurrent programming.
爬虫是并发编程的一个更现实的例子。
Yeah, and just remind you,
提醒你一下，
you know basically the idea is that,
基本上这个想法是，
you started with url for some web page,
你从一些网页的 url 开始，
you fetch, you fetch the web page that might have more urls,
你获取的可能包含更多 url 的网页，
and when you basically proceed,
当你继续的时候，
you know then fetching those web pages,
然后取回那些网页，
you know looking at those urls and you keep going.
查着这些 url ，并继续前进。
The idea is to crawl basically the whole Internet
这个想法是爬取整个互联网，
you know for all the web pages that are exist,
存在的所有网页，
and of course some urls might point back to a web page you already visited,
当然，一些 url 可能指向你已经访问过的网页，
and so goal is to actually not visit the same web page twice.
所以目标是不会两次访问同一个网页。
And so the goal of the exercise is a couple of goals,
所以这个练习有几个目标，
you want to achieve, right.
你想达到的。
One is IO concurrency,
一个是 IO 并发性，
the fetch operation is may take a long time,
爬取操作可能需要很长时间，
maybe it's a web page,
也许一个网页，
it's on the other side of the world,
它在世界的另一边，
you know maybe it goes over slow networks,
可能它是通过低速网络传输的，
and while you know one thread is sort of fetching that page,
当一个线程正在爬取那个页面时，
you would like to be able to fetch other other other pages,
你希望能够爬取其他页面，
another goals is correctness goal or performance goal,
另一个目标是正确性目标或性能目标，
namely fetch one fetch url once,
即只爬取一次 url ，
and you know presumably your goals are like to exploit multiple cores,
假设你的目标是开发多个核心，
you know if you have multiple cores doing work in parallelism.
你有多个核心并行工作。
Okay?
好的?
So, what I'd like to do,
所以，我想做的是，
before actually talking about the concurrent solutions,
在真正讨论并发解决方案之前，
first let me show you a simple serial solution,
首先，让我展示一个简单的顺序的解决方案，
so that we,
所以我们，
you know we have something to talk about as a baseline.
让我们有一些东西可以作为基线来谈论。
So, so I have three solutions in here.
所以，这里我有三个解决方案。
Run them, go run.
运行它们，go run.
A serial solution, and one of the mutex, one of the channels,
一个顺序的解决方案，一个使用互斥锁，一个使用通道，
you know you see the more or less they produce the same results,
你看到，它们产生的结果或多或少是一样的，
you know two found, one missing, two found,
两个找到，一个丢失，两个找到，
the only difference is that,
唯一的区别是，
the order of the output slightly different once in a while,
输出的顺序偶尔会略有不同，
and of course it had to do concurrency.
当然，它必须进行并发操作。
Okay, so, the main function calls in Serial,
好的，主函数调用的 Serial ，
with the starting url, fetcher and then an empty map,
使用起始 url ， fetcher ，然后是一个空映射，
and then the serial solution is basically sort of standard sequential recursive solution,
顺序方案是一种标准的顺序递归解，
we first check if we already visited the url that's passed into us,
我们首先检查是否已经访问了传递给我们的 url ，
if we did, you know we return immediately,
如果我们访问了，我们会立即返回，
otherwise we mark this visit,
否则我们把它标记为访问，
we'll fetch the url,
我们去获取 url ，
that this is a bunch of urls,
这是一堆 url ，
we look for all the urls,
我们查找所有的 url ，
and go basically Serial again, right,
然后再次调用 Serial ，
this is you know sequential solution,
这就是顺序解决方案，
that's what I expected.
正是我所期望的。
And you know your goal which is basically write concurrent version of this.
你的目标是编写这个的并发版本。
And so, what I like to do is
所以，我想做的是，
actually to make the class a little bit interactive,
让课堂变得更具互动性，
I wanna go switch over to breakout rooms,
我想切换到分组会议室，
and what we're gonna do is
我们要做的是，
basically put four to five of you in a single breakout room,
让你们四到五个人在一个分组会议室，
for about ten minutes,
大概十分钟，
and I would like you to do is,
我希望你们做的是，
share your solution with each other and discuss it,
分享你们的解决方案，并进行讨论，
so maybe the best way to go about it is,
所以也许最好的办法就是，
one of you, you know you get into a room,
你们中的一个人，你进了一个房间，
one of the persons in the room,
房间里的一个人，
basically screen shares their solution
通过屏幕分享他们的解决方案，
and discuss what has been one of the issues,
并讨论其中一个问题，
that you see running into,
你所遇到的，
and other people can comment or share other solutions,
其他人可以评论或分享其他解决方案，
let's just get into a discussion
让我们来讨论一下，
and meet some other students in the class.
并看看班上的其他同学。
Any questions about that?
对于这个，有什么问题吗？
Okay, good, let me go back,
好的，让我回去，
to sharing my screen again,
再次分享我的屏幕，
can everybody see my screen again.
大家能不能再看到我的屏幕。
Yep, looks good.
是的，看起来不错。
Good, thank you.
很好，谢谢你。
Okay, so hopefully that was interesting,
好的，希望这很有趣，
let me you know talk about you know the solutions that I have,
让我谈论一下我的解决方案，
they're posted on the schedule page,
它们已经放在课程表页面上，
if you haven't, you can look concurrently with me,
如果你还没有，你可以和我一起看，
if you want to.
如果你想的话。
You should you know let me walk through the mutex version first,
让我先看一遍互斥锁版本，
and then I'll walk through the channel one second.
稍后再看通道的版本。
So here's the mutex one,
所以，这是互斥锁版本，
mutex one the declareation struct with the have both the map and the mutex,
互斥锁版本声明了具有映射和互斥锁的结构，
and the map needs to be protected by mutex,
映射需要由互斥锁保护，
because it's going to be concurrent access to the map,
因为会对映射进行并发访问，
map by itself it's not thread-safe,
映射本身并不是线程安全的，
it's up to the programmer to actually make the map thread-safe.
取决于程序员使映射是线程安全的。
And the concurrently mutex one more short similar to the serial one,
互斥锁版本跟顺序版本很像，
except whenever there's stage, basically takes a lock out,
除了有一个阶段使用了锁，
you know so we'll take the lock,
所以我们获取锁，
we look at the url has already being fetched,
我们查看 url 是否已经被爬取，
it hasn't been fetched,
如果它没有被爬取，
we markd has now being fetched,
我们现在把它标记为爬取，
what hasn't been fetched and we unlock,
还没有被爬取，我们解锁，
and we kept this already value
我们保留这个 already 的值，
to decide whether we should return or not.
决定我们是否应该返回。
And then, you know we this goroutines starts fetching a page,
然后，这个 goroutine 开始爬取页面，
gets a bunch of urls back,
取回一堆 url ，
and then for every url back,
然后对于每个返回的 url ，
it creates a new goroutine here on this side,
它在这边创造了一个新的 goroutine ，
passes in the url,
传入 url ，
but goroutine is supposed to fetch and crawl.
goroutine 会爬取。
The only sort of other interesting thing here is that,
这里唯一有趣的是，
it uses something about WaitGroup,
它使用了关于 WaitGroup 的一些东西，
and WaitGroup is a very convenient primitive
WaitGroup 是一个非常方便的原语，
to keep track how many threads you still have active,
用于跟踪你有多少活动线程，
and when you can terminate.
什么时候可以终止。
And this was a big issue in this particular assignment,
这是这次任务中的一个大问题，
that if you terminated too early,
如果你终止得太早，
then you didn't crawl the web pages.
那你还没有爬取网页。
And so you need to keep track whatever,
所以你需要跟踪，
whatever there's still outstanding web pages to be crawled,
还有什么网页需要抓取，
sync.WaitGroup is a very easily,
sync.WaitGroup 非常简单，
basically every time you call thread, you call Add,
每次你调用线程，调用 Add ，
and then when the thread terminates, you call Done,
然后当线程终止时，调用 Done ，
and we could conveniently do that in a defer statement.
我们可以方便的在 defer 语句中做到。
And then the main thread that is waiting for all the thread to terminated,
然后主线程等待所有线程结束，
just goes wait
只是等待，
and Wait will return until every thread,
Wait 将返回，直到每个线程，
that will started for every Add(1),
开始时的每个 Add(1) ，
if all those threads actually has been exited.
如果所有这些线程都已经退出。
That's the mutex version.
这是互斥锁的版本。
And you can think about sync wait as
你可以将 sync wait 看作是，
sort of being internally implemented using condition variable.
条件变量的内部实现。
Okay, let me look at the channel version,
好的，让我来看看通道版本，
so here's channel version
这是通道版本，
is basically sort of organized as mapreduce lab,
基本上是按照 mapreduce 实验组织的，
where there's a coordinator and workers,
有协调者和工作者，
so, we start of, you know we start of creating a coordinator thread,
所以，我们开始创建一个协调者线程，
and the way we do that actually is,
我们做这一点的方式是，
we make a channel,
我们创建一个通道，
and then we pass the channel into the coordinator,
然后将通道传递给 coordinator ，
the coordinator of course has to start with a url, the beginning url,
coordinator 当然必须从开始 url 开始，
so we need to supply that on the channel,
所以我们需要在通道上提供这些信息，
that's the most convenient thing to do,
这是最方便的事情，
as we'll see in a second.
我们马上会看到。
But, you know to send it on the channel,
但是，要把它发送给通道，
we basically have to create a goroutine,
我们需要创造一个 goroutine ，
because otherwise we deadlock here,
否则，我们会陷入死锁，
we, this is a difficult thing,
这是一件困难的事情，
we're going to just send that value on the channel.
我们将在通道上发送那个值。
So let's look at the coordinator,
让我们来看一下 coordinator ，
here's the coordinator, it doesn't use any locks at all,
这是 coordinator ，它不使用任何锁，
because you know the data structures,
因为数据结构，
that there's no data structures actually being shared,
这里没有实际共享的数据结构，
like fetched,
比如 fetched ，
the map that actually keep track of which urls actually fetched,
映射跟踪哪些 url 被爬取，
is actually the only access within the coordinator.
只在 coordinator 中访问。
So the coordinator got,
所以 coordinator 获得，
you know when we called it initially, we've got,
当我们初始调用它的时候，我们得到，
it has one url, checks the fetched map,
它有一个 url ，检查 fetched 映射，
and for every url,
对于每个 url ，
then it goes basically you know cycles through reach the channel,
然后它循环到达通道
using a range statement,
使用 range 语句，
and basically what this does is,
它所做的是，
just keep reading the channel,
只要继续读取通道，
and grab the next value, grab next value, grab next value,
然后获取下一个值，获取下一个值，获取下一个值，
so basically grabs the url,
所以就是获取 url ，
we know there's one init,
我们知道有一个初始化，
because we put it on, when we created it.
因为我们在创建它时，放入的。
And then, for that url,
然后，对于那个 url ，
we sort of roughly do the same thing as the,
我们做的事情类似于，
concurrent as the mutex one,
并发类似于互斥锁版本，
you know we see the url has already been fetched,
我们看到 url 已经被获取，
if it has been fetched, then we're done,
如果已经获取，那我们完成了，
otherwise we will create a Go worker to actually fetch that url.
否则，我们创建一个 Go worker 来获取那个 url 。
And we keep track of how many outstanding workers we have,
我们会记录我们有多少 worker ，
so n is counting number of workers,
n 是统计 worker 的数量，
and only when n is 0,
只有当 n 为 0 时，
do we terminate the coordinator,
我们才会终止 coordinator ，
to make sure that basically we have fetched all the web pages,
确保我们已经获取了所有网页，
that were supposed to be fetching.
我们想要爬取的。
And you look at worker,
如果你查看 worker ，
worker basically calls Fetch,
worker 调用 Fetch ，
this call happens completely parallel with any other workers.
这个调用是与其他 worker 并行发生的。
If it actually fetch some url from that web page,
如果它从网页获取了一些 url ，
it basically writes all those urls to the channel,
它将所有这些 url 写入通道，
and so the coordinator will get all those channels through range statements,
coordinator 通过 range 语句获取所有这些通道，
and then when it's done,
然后当它完成的时候，
writing all the urls through channel,
通过通道写入所有 url ，
then the coordinator worker exits,
然后 coordinator worker 退出，
and that will you know at some point decrease you know n,
在某一时刻，减少 n ，
and then at the end of,
然后在最后，
and that's it basically.
基本上就是这样。
Okay?
好的?
So those are the two solutions,
所以这就是两个解决方案，
any questions about these?
关于这些，有什么问题吗？
Is it all clear?
都清楚了吗？
There's a question in chat.
聊天中有个问题。
Okay, let me get my chat list back up.
好的，让我找回我的聊天列表。
Okay, so the question is,
好的，所以问题是，
when ch has a value in it,
当 ch 有值时，
when all other threads be idle,
当所有其他线程空闲时，
if it's the case,
如果是这种情况，
that's, since this is not a buffered channel,
由于这不是缓冲通道，
but you know there's going to be only one request in the channel at the time,
通道中同时只会有一个请求，
and so all the threads you know will be appended to the channel one by one.
所有线程都会被一个接一个地加到通道中。
But doesn't that make the program sequential,
但这不是让程序顺序化了吗，
because no two threads are running in parallel,
因为没有两个线程并行运行，
except the main thread and one.
除了主线程和一个线程。
Well the fetchers will still happen in parallel,
好的， fetcher 仍然会并行发生，
those are presuming the expensive operation,
这些是昂贵的操作，
where those go out across the Internet.
这些需要通过互联网。
Got it, thank you.
知道了，谢谢。
Okay, let me switch back to my other screen,
好的，让我切换回我的另一个屏幕，
and talk a little bit about RPC,
稍微讨论一下 RPC ，
since that's the other thing tool that you need for the labs.
因为这是实验里需要的另一个工具。
We're not going to say a ton about it,
关于这个我们不会说太多，
but there's RPC which stands for remote procedure calls.
但是 RPC 表示远程过程调用。
And basically the goal, you know the goal of RPC system,
RPC 系统的目标，
like the one that goal has,
比如一个目标是，
so basically RPCs behave roughly similar to procedure calls,
RPC 的行为与过程调用大致相似，
local procedure calls the execute on the stack, right.
在栈上运行的本地过程调用，
And so the goal is,
所以目标是，
for example if you have a client,
如果你有一个客户端，
in RPC terminology, the caller typically called the client
在 RPC 术语中，调用方通常称为客户端，
and callee is called server.
被呼叫方称为服务器。
So you have a function fn,
所以你有一个函数 fn ，
you know we're calling with x and y
使用 x y 调用，
and then at the server,
然后在服务器上，
there's the implementation of this function.
有这个函数的实现。
And so there's a function fn whatever x you know y int,
所以有一个函数 fn(x, y int) ，
and you know it returns you know whatever does some computation,
它返回，无论做什么计算，
when they can use this returns x plus y.
可以返回 x+y 。
And so, what we would like to have happen
所以，我们希望发生的事，
or like the model that we would like to ourselves to think about is that,
或者我们考虑的模型是，
when the client calls this function fn,
当客户端调用该函数 fn 时，
the RPC system will make sure,
RPC 系统会确保，
that there's any corresponding application happening on the server side,
在服务器端发生对应的应用程序，
passes the arguments x and y you know to the server,
将参数 x 和 y 传递给服务器，
the code runs on the server,
代码在服务器上运行，
it you know returns a result you see,
它会返回你看到的结果，
and that result is communicating back to the client,
那个结果是向客户端发回信息，
and you know and then fn will resume, will return,
然后 fn 恢复，返回，
and the client will return,
客户端会返回，
will resume with the x plus y,
将返回 x+y ，
in the value of x plus y as z, right.
返回 x+y 的值到 z 。
So this looks like,
所以这看起来，
even though the programs are running on different computers,
尽管这些程序运行在不同的计算机上，
you know they're actually have boundary here,
它们实际上在这里是有界限的，
it looks like you know they make a regular procedure calls.
看起来像做一个普通的过程调用，
We'll see in a second,
我们一会会看到，
actually we can make a lot of similarities,
实际上，我们可以找到很多相似之处，
so it's possible to make them behave very similar,
所以让它们的行为非常相似，
but you'll see there's also a sort of a fundamental difference,
但你也会发现有一个根本的不同，
and actually has what to do with distributed computing.
与分布式计算有关系。
But before getting there,
但在到达那里之前，
let me first of sketch out how you can make this work.
首先我大概说一下它是如何工作的。
And this is sort of roughly, let's Go does too.
这是一种粗略的 Go 说做的。
So, so the way you think about it is that,
所以，你可以这样想，
when the client,
当客户端，
so here our program,
所以这是我们的程序，
and when the client calls the function fn with x and y in it,
当客户端使用 x y 调用函数 fn 时，
what it does, it actually calls something that's called stub,
它实际上调用的称为 stub 的东西，
and stub is basically local function,
stub 是本地函数，
you know call fn and with two arguments declared that x and y,
调用 fn ，并用两个参数 x 和 y ，
and basically what the stub does,
stub 所做的，
you know think this is a stub procedure,
考虑这是一个 stub 过程，
but stub procedure basically does,
stub 过程所做的，
build a message, you know saying which function needs to be called,
构建一个消息，表示哪个函数需要被调用，
the arguments of the function,
函数的参数，
you know the types of arguments,
参数的类型，
the values of these arguments etc etc.
参数的值等等。
And then what the stub does,
然后 stub 所做的，
actually it sends it over the network
它通过网络发送，
to corresponding stub at the server,
到服务器上对应的 stub ，
so server receives this message,
服务器接收到这个消息，
and basically you know takes this message,
取得这个消息，
and marshall unmarshall it, is a term,
反序列化它，这是一个术语，
that's being used to
它用来，
basically convert values from byte arrays, byte arrays back to values,
将值从字节数组转换回值，
and then calls you know this function fn at the server,
然后在服务器上调用这个函数 fn ，
here's you know fn x, blah blah blah.
这是 fn x 等等。
So stub basically calls the function,
所以， stub 调用这个函数，
the function returns back into the stub,
这个函数返回到 stub ，
this stub marshals you know the response value like z x plus y,
这个 stub 序列化响应值，比如 z x+y ，
and since that back you know to the client stub,
它返回到客户端 stub ，
and client stub is still waiting,
而且客户端 stub 仍在等待，
so basically the client stub the way it actually works,
所以，客户端 stub 的工作方式，
it sends out the request and then wait for the response,
它发出请求，然后等待响应，
when the response comes back in,
当响应回来的时候，
you know it unmarshalls,
它反序列化，
and then you know returns the value to the client, right.
然后将值返回给客户端。
So, basically these two stubs,
所以，这两个 stub ，
sort of make a remote procedure call look like a regular procedure call,
使远程过程调用看起来像是常规过程调用，
for almost you can't tell.
因为你几乎看不出来。
And the key, and these stubs are generally you know automatically generated,
这些键，这些 stub 通常是自动生成的，
so the compiler, and in case Go compiler
在 Go 的编译器中，
that will generate two stubs for you,
会为你生成两个 stub ，
and do the marshalling and unmarshalling arguments for you,
并为你序列化和反序列化参数，
and and that how it goes.
这就是它说做的。
Also the, so when you're doing it from the server to the client,
所以当你从服务器到客户端时，
there's also another stub again?
还有另一个 stub 吗？
You basically return back to the first stub.
你会返回到第一个 stub 。
So this stub makes a procedure call,
所以这个 stub 发出一个过程调用，
to make a calls the procedure fn,
发出一个过程调用 fn ，
that procedure returns right into the stub,
这个过程直接返回到 stub ，
because stub called it.
因为 stub 调用的它。
Oh, it's the same stub, that it goes in.
哦，这是同一个 stub 。
Exactly.
没错。
Got it.
明白了。
Okay?
好的?
Okay, so, let me show you how this plays out inside of Go,
好的，让我来展示这是如何在 Go 中进行的，
and by showing you a very simple key-value server.
通过展示一个非常简单的键值服务器。
And you'll see,
你会看到，
it doesn't look exactly our procedure calls,
它看起来不完全是我们的过程调用，
but it's pretty close.
但已经很接近了。
So the typical thing is that,
所以典型的情况是，
you actually declare typical convention should be in Go
在 Go 中的典型转换，
that you declare the argument structure,
你声明参数结构，
and so we're going to implement two procedures,
所以，我们将实现两个过程，
two remote procedures,
两个远程过程，
one is put and one is get,
一个是 put ，一个是 get ，
and put is basically put arguments is,
put 的参数是，
the arguments through the put and put replies to response,
参数通过 put ， put 返回响应，
similar there's get arguments with request,
类似地，有一个 get 参数请求，
where the arguments through the request get procedure and the reply.
参数通过 get 请求，然后返回。
And so let me first look at the server,
所以让我先来看服务器，
so here are two functions,
这里有两个函数，
you know actually the two function that we're going to be calling on the server,
是我们要在服务器上调用的两个函数，
I think I'll skip down for that for a second.
我想我先跳过这一步。
So we actually.
所以我们实际上。
Let me talk about it a little bit,
让我稍微说一下，
so this is the client side,
这是客户端，
so the client calls a function get,
客户端调用一个函数 get ，
and what inside of get,
在 get 之中，
you know you know this function actually connects to the server,
这个函数连接到服务器，
and see exactly what that means,
看看这到底是什么意思，
it, it fills in the arguments,
它填充了参数，
and allocates a response,
并分配响应，
and then calls this procedure client.Call call,
然后调用这个过程调用 client.Call ，
you can think about this as a generic stub,
你可以认为这是一个通用的 stub ，
that basically takes the method that needs to be called in server,
使用需要在服务端调用的方法，
and the arguments and the reply,
以及参数和响应，
and so Call has three arguments,
所以 Call 有三个参数，
the method, the argument and response,
方法，参数和响应，
and Call internally will send marshal the arguments,
而 Call 内部会发送序列化的参数，
send the message to the server over the connection,
通过连接发送消息到服务器，
and wait for the response reply,
等待响应返回，
when the reply comes in,
当响应回来时，
the reply structure will be filled in by the Call stub,
reply 结构由 Call stub 填充，
and then when that's done,
然后当这件事完成后，
then return at the Call call.
然后返回到 Call 调用。
And basically put looks exactly the same way.
基本上， put 看起来是完全一样的。
And so on the server side,
所以，在服务器端，
you know let's see how that is implemented,
让我们看看这是如何实现的，
the server has a key-value map,
服务器有键值映射，
this is nothing else than a regular Go map,
只是一个常规的 Go 映射，
and, let me see actually the key-value struct,
让我看看键值结构，
declared somewhere,
在某个地方声明的，
oh, sorry it's right above it.
哦，抱歉，它就在上面。
So there's a struct called KV,
所以这里有一个结构叫做 KV ，
that actually has mutex and a map in it,
它有一个互斥锁和一个映射，
and the map is like, we're going to do the put and get operations on.
这个映射是我们要放入和获取操作的。
And there's a little preamble,
这里有一个小的前言，
that you need to sort of write to setup a server,
你需要编写来设置服务器，
but here it is,
但就是这样，
you know you basically allocate a new server object,
基本上，分配一个新的服务器对象，
and then this is the key operation rpcs.Register(kv) will,
然后这里是键操作 rpcs.Register(kv) ，
register basically all the methods,
注册所有方法，
that are implemented on the KV struct with the RPC server,
在 RPC 服务器上 KV 结构上实现的方法，
with one twist, the methods only the capital named,
不同的是，这些由大写字母命名的方法，
methods with the capital will actually be recorded,
用大写字母的方法会被记录，
and so basically Go use capital names to indicate public methods,
Go 使用大写字母名称来表示公共方法，
and a method with a small small caps is in private method,
而小写的方法是私有方法，
so only, basically RPC register exports only capitalized methods,
所以， rpcs.Register 只导出大写的方法，
for example, here's a method below,
例如，下面是一个方法，
here's a Get method, it has a capital letter,
这里是 Get 方法，它有大写字母，
and by calling Register,
通过调用 Register ，
that method is now callable by client to the connection the server.
这个方法可以通过客户端调用服务端。
So the server internally,
所以，在服务器内部，
basically it creates a TCP connection,
它创建一个 TCP 连接，
and waits on TCP connection
并等待 TCP 连接，
to get a request or a new connection request for TCP connection,
获得 TCP 连接的返回，
and then calls rpcs.ServeConn to serve that TCP connection,
然后调用 rpcs.ServeConn 来提供 TCP 连接，
and basically every message that comes in over that you know connection,
基本上，每一条通过连接的消息，
it will automatically find the right method,
它会自动找到正确的方法，
you know is associated with the message,
与消息相关联，
and call that method with unmarshalled arguments and marshal reply.
使用反序列化的参数调用方法，并序列化回复。
So, for example if the client calls Get,
例如，如果客户端调用 GET ，
you know connects to it will call makes this connection into existence,
它使这个连接存在，
and then if the client calls call with Get,
然后，如果客户端使用 Get 调用 Call ，
then this Get function will be run.
然后将运行这个 Get 函数。
And as you can see the Get function,
如你所见，这个 Get 函数，
first thing it does,
它做的第一件事是，
it actually takes a lock out,
它先获取一个锁，
because multiple clients could be calling the server,
因为多个客户端可能会调用服务器，
and so there will be multiple goroutines running at the same time,
会有多个 goroutine 同时运行，
perhaps invoking Get and Put,
也许会调用 Get 和 Put ，
and so they were manipulating the the map concurrently,
它们同时操作映射，
and so we need to make sure that,
所以，我们需要确保，
you know those that is done in an atomic way,
这些是以原子的方式完成的，
so therefore we use locks.
所以，我们使用锁。
So the Get function looks at the key into the map,
所以， Get 函数查看映射中的键，
looks at the key in the map, returns basically the value,
查看映射中的键，然后返回值，
if there's no entry in the map,
如果映射中没有条目，
it will return ErrNoKey,
它将返回 ErrNoKey ，
otherwise it will return the appropriate value,
否则，它会返回适当的值，
and that's it.
就是这样。
And so on the server side,
在服务器端，
when these Get function returns,
当这些 Get 函数返回时，
it will marshal its response,
它会序列化自己的回应，
sends a response back to client,
将响应发回客户端，
the client will set it unmarshal,
客户端对其进行反序列化，
it actually return it to the caller.
并将其返回给调用者。
Okay, so that makes sense?
好的，这能理解吗？
So that's sort of do a simple key-value server in action.
所以这是在做一个简单的键值服务器。
Okay, I want to make one more point,
好的，我想再说一点，
which is an important point,
这是很重要的一点，
and in the end,
最后，
what's important to think about is,
重要的是要考虑的是，
what RPC semantics are under failures.
RPC 失败的语义是什么。
So there are different types of semantics possible,
所以可能存在不同类型的语义，
something is called at-least-once,
某些东西称为至少调用一次，
this all has to do with,
这一切所做的，
what does the client do if the server fails.
如果服务器发生故障，客户端所做的事情。
So let's say the client sends request, the server crashes,
我们假设客户端发送了请求，然后服务器崩溃了，
and, of course now at some point, client will timeout,
当然，在某个时刻，客户端将会超时，
and it doesn't know whether the operation actually happened or not happened,
它不知道操作是否真的发生了，
and at-least-once RPC semantics means,
至少一次 RPC 语义意味着，
that the client will automatically retry and will keep going,
客户端将自动重试并继续，
so it has executed at least once.
所以它至少执行一次。
The downside of course at-least-once is that,
至少一次的缺点是，
you know the same operation might be executed multiple times,
同一个操作可能会被多次执行，
so for example, if you do a put,
比如，如果你做一个 put ，
you know the put might be actually executed multiple times
put 可能会被执行多次，
at at-least-one RPC system.
在至少一次 RPC 系统中。
So that's not appropriate for many applications,
所以这并不适用于许多应用程序，
so another type of semantics,
所以，另一种语义，
that's common in RPC systems is at-most-once,
常出现在 RPC 系统中的是最多一次，
so the corresponding server request actually executed either zero times or once,
相应的服务器请求执行零次或一次，
but no more than once,
但不会超过一次，
and the way you know that is typically implemented by filtering duplicates,
它实现的方式是通过过滤重复，
you actually doing that in in later labs,
你会在后面的实验中做这个，
that could could be the case,
可能是这种情况，
that actually both requests actually come through,
两个请求到达，
maybe the networks like temporary partition,
也许网络临时分裂，
the server actually gets both request,
服务器收到了这两个请求，
and the server has to arrange that,
服务器必须安排，
it detects a resend request and doesn't execute it twice.
它检测到重新发送的请求，并且不执行两次。
Now, of course ideally,
当然，理想情况下，
you might actually want exactly-once,
你可能需要正好一次，
because that's actually what the normal procedure would be,
因为这是正常过程所做的，
like if you call a procedure in your server in a normal sequential program,
就像你在一个正常的顺序程序中调用过程，
execution exactly once,
正好执行一次，
it's never possible to be at-least-once or at-most-once.
它永远不可能是至少一次或最多一次。
This turns out to be actually very hard to arrange,
事实证明，这很难[安排]，
this requires you know basically have to maintain state on disk,
这需要管理状态在磁盘上，
and tend to be expensive,
而且往往很昂贵，
and in fact in practice very few RPC systems are exactly-once,
事实上，很少有 RPC 系统是正好一次，
although in the lab,
虽然在实验中，
you're going to build actually one in lab 3,
你要在实验 3 中构建一个，
you're going to actually build an RPC system that's basically exactly-once.
你需要构建一个正好一次的 RPC 系统。
Okay?
好的?
In practice, Go's RPC system is at most once,
实际上， Go 的 RPC 系统是最多一次，
so if you do a call,
所以如果你发起一个调用，
and you do the call across TCP channel,
你通过 TCP 通道进行调用，
the TCP channel will make sure that there are no duplicates,
TCP 通道将确保不存在重复项，
and so and and RPC system will either execute once or none at all,
RPC 系统要么执行一次，要么根本不执行，
and then in the case and return an error,
然后在这种情况下，返回一个错误，
and then of course the application may retry,
然后当然应用程序可以重试，
but you know it's the applications responsibility,
但这是应用程序的责任，
to deal with the problems of duplication and failed messages.
处理重复和失败消息的问题。
Okay, so here's the sort of key point, correct,
好的，这就是关键点，
the fact that their failures,
它们的失败，
basically makes you know RPCs not identical to procedure calls,
使 RPC 与过程调用不同，
so you know the goal is,
所以目标是，
to make them look as similar as possible, actually not identical,
让它们看起来尽可能地相似，实际上并不完全相同，
and really the thing that exposes the differences is failures or the server crashing.
导致出现差异的是故障或服务器崩溃。
Any questions about this quick intro for RPC?
关于 RPC 的快速介绍，有什么问题吗？
Okay, if not, then I want to stop the lecture here,
好的，如果没有，我就在这里结束了，
so there are people that need to go
所以有些人需要离开，
or students need to go to the next class,
或者学生需要上下一节课，
you can go to the next class,
你可以去下一节课，
I'll be hanging around,
我会在线，
so if there's any more questions,
所以如果还有什么问题，
I'll be happy to to answer them,
我很乐意回答，
and stick around for a little while.
在这里逗留一段时间。
In the meantime, enjoy lab 1 and good luck with it.
同时，享受实验 1 ，并祝你们好运。